Inventory of the Stiles Collection of John B. Tabb 1870-1968
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Stiles Collection of John B. Tabb 1870-1968
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 35
1 linear feet
John B. Tabb
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On her death in 1967, May Evelyn Stiles left her collection of Tabb materials to Sue W. Jones of Charlottesville, VA. Miss Jones donated the materials to the Special Collection department in 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Bannister Tabb was born 22 March 1845 on his father's plantation, "The Forest", in Amelia County, Virginia. His parents were John Yelverton and Marianne Bertrand Archer Tabb.
A Confederate blockade runner during the Civil War, Tabb's ship, the "Siren", was captured 4 June 1864 and he was imprisoned at Pt. Lookout, Maryland There he met and befriended the Georgian poet Sidney Lanier. They remained close friends until Lanier's death in 1881. Through their friendship, Tabb began to write poetry.
After the war, Tabb studied theology, expecting to become an Episcopalian priest. However, he became interested in Catholicism and converted in September 1872. He subsequently entered St. Charles College, Ellicott City, Maryland, from which he graduated in 1875.
Tabb enrolled in St. Mary's Seminary in Baltimore in 1881 and was ordained as a priest on 20 December 1884, though he never held a parish. He returned to St. Charles College and taught English until blindness forced him to retire in 1907.
He began to write poetry during the Civil War, but his first volume, Poems, was not published until 1882. His metaphysical little poems gained popularity after the publication of a second volume of the same name in 1894, and he published regularly thereafter.
Poor eyesight had plagued Tabb since boyhood and he was completely blind when he died in Ellicott City, MD on 9 November 1909.
Tabb's major works include Poems (1882), An Octave to Mary (1893), Poems (1894), Lyrics (1897), Bone Rules: Or, Skeleton of English Grammar (1897), Child Verse (1899), Two Lyrics (1900), Later Lyrics (1902), The Rosary on Rhyme (1884), Quipps and Quiddits (1907) and Later Poems (1910).
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of approximately 275 items of various types concerning the priest-poet, Father John B. Tabb, collected by his friend and admirer, Mary Evelyn Stiles of Richmond. Contained in the collection are a number of manuscript poems by Tabb, photocopies of letters from Tabb to Sidney Lanier, Gordon Blair, and others (1877-1909 originals at the Virginia Historical Society), and the letters and notebooks of Miss Stiles that pertain to Tabb. The collection spans the years 1877 to 1968.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by subject and chronological therein.
Contents List
- Emma Gray Trigg items 1968-1971 (Box-folder 1.1)
- Sue Jones Correspondence 1968 (Box-folder 1.2)
- Mary Evelyn Stiles Correspondence, n.d. 1915-1952 (Box-folder 1.3)
- Cards made from Tabb poems, ca. 1916 (Box-folder 1.4)
- Biography of Tabb by Stiles, n.d. (Box-folder 1.5)
- Sister Mary Paulina Finn to Stiles 1906-1919 (Box-folder 1.6)
- Miscellaneous Stiles papers, n.d. 1897-1922 (Box-folder 1.7)
- Miscellaneous Stiles papers, n.d. (Box-folder 1.8)
- Ms Tabb Notes and Poems 1897-1906 (Box-folder 1.9)
- Tabb poems, n.d. (Box-folder 1.10)
- Tabb poems, n.d. 1897 (Box-folder 1.11)
- Philo Tabb to J.B. Tabb, n.d. (Box-folder 1.12)
- Clippings about Tabb (Box-folder 1.13)
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1896-1900 (Box-folder 2.1)
  All letters photocopies
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1901-1902 (Box-folder 2.2)
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1903-1904 (Box-folder 2.3)
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1905 (Box-folder 2.4)
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1906-1907 (Box-folder 2.5)
- Letters: Tabb to Gordon Blair 1908-1909 (Box-folder 2.6)
- Letters: Tabb to Louisa Coleman Gordon Blair (Lulie) 1898-1909 (Box-folder 2.7)
- Letters: Tabb to Sidney and Mary Day Lanier 1877-1881 (Box-folder 2.8)
- Poems by Lanier 1880 (Box-folder 2.9)
- Letter to Maria, n.d. (Box-folder 2.10)
- Notebook 1910-1913 (Box-folder 3.1)
- Notebook 1903-1916 (Box-folder 3.2)
- Notebook John Bannister Tabb: A Study of his Poetry by Thomas T. Price 1896 (Box-folder 3.3)
- Notebook, n.d. 1915 (Box-folder 3.4)
- Child Verse: Poems Grave and Gay by Tabb 1899 (Box-folder 3.5)
- Negative of a photograph, n.d. to be removed (Box-folder 3.6)
- Articles about Tabb 1945, 1953, 1956 (Box-folder 3.7)